Finding aid to Upton family papers SSC.MS.00164
Sophia Smith Collection
Upton family papers
1853-1971
Sophia Smith Collection
Upton family
SSC.MS.00164
2.438 linear feet (7 containers)
The Upton Family papers include materials created by Cornelia Babcock Upton and Winslow Upton, and their two daughters, both graduates of Smith College. This collection includes correspondence, diaries, and notes by Cornelia Upton documenting her travels in America, Hawaii, Alaska, Africa, and the Far East. Bacteriologist Margaret Upton and librarian Eleanor Upton's papers include documents of a children's club in Providence, RI, to which they belonged.
Biographical / Historical
Cornelia A. Babcock Upton was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1854 and graduated from Providence, Rhode Island High School in 1874. In 1882 she married Winslow Upton, professor of astronomy at Brown University. The couple had two daughters, Eleanor and Margaret (see below). Upton's "chief interest" was the Auxiliary Board of Missions of the Episcopal Church. Following the death of her husband in 1931, she lived with her daughter Eleanor in New Haven, Connecticut; she died there in 1941.
Eleanor Stuart Upton was born in Lebanon Springs, New York in 1886. She graduated from Smith College in 1909, obtained an M.A. from Brown University in 1910, and a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1930. Between 1910 and 1914 she worked for a variety of social welfare organizations in Boston and Providence; as a tutor from 1914-16; and as a librarian at the John Carter Brown Library in Providence from 1916-21. She became an assistant librarian at Yale University in 1921 and was a cataloger at the Forbes Library in Northampton, Massachusetts from 1952 to 1962. She died in Hadley, Massachusetts, in 1974.
Margaret Frances Upton was born in Providence, Rhode Island in 1890. She graduated from Smith College in 1912, obtained an M.A. from Brown University in 1914, and a Ph.D. from Yale University in 1925. She taught science and bacteriology on the secondary and undergraduate level, and worked as a lab technician and research assistant, primarily at St. Luke's Hospital in Newburgh, New York and at Cooley Dickinson Hospital in Northampton, Massachusetts. She died in Hadley Massachusetts in 1967.
Scope and Contents
The Upton Family papers consist of biographical material, club records, correspondence, diaries, memorabilia, photographs, and writings. Included are correspondence, diaries, and notes by Cornelia Upton which document her extensive travels (1876-1905), as well as correspondence from missionaries in a variety of locations (1899-1927). The lives of Margaret and Eleanor Upton are documented through the records of the "Quier Kyds" (1897-1900), a children's club in Providence, RI, to which they belonged; as well as Eleanor's line-a-day diaries (1896-1920, 1924-26) and her dissertation, "Guide to Sources of English History, 1603-1660."
Related Material
Additional material on Eleanor and Margaret Upton is located in the Smith College Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Episcopal church--Missions--History--Sources; Family--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Hawaii--Description and travel--Sources; Latin America--Description and travel; Missionaries--Africa--Biography--Sources; Missionaries--Alaska--Biography--Sources; Missionaries--China--Biography--Sources; Missionaries--Japan--Biography--Sources; Missionaries--Middle East--Biography--Sources; Oceania--Description and travel--Sources; Women scientists--United States--Biography--Sources; Manuscripts; diaries; Writings; Photographs.; memorabilia; correspondence; United States--Description and travel--Sources; Upton family; Upton, Cornelia A. Babcock, 1854-1941; Upton, Eleanor Stuart, 1886-; Upton, Margaret Frances, 1890- 1967; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Upton, Eleanor Stuart; Upton, Margaret Frances; Upton, Eleanor; Upton, Margaret; unknown; Upton family
- Eleanor and Margaret Upton
  - An Earth Bound Astonomer, Winslow Upton: A Memoir by Eleanor S. Upton and Margaret F. Upton, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Quier Kyds" children's club
  - Minutes, 1897-1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters and souvenirs, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper, 1897-1900 (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
  - Plays and "Photo of Peterkins", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, songs, and miscellaneous material, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photostats of the Quier Kyds newspaper, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Eleanor S. Upton
  - Dissertation: "Guide to Sources of English History, 1603-1660"
    - Introduction, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Working copy, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ms. original of introduction, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Typed copy, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Line-a-day diaries, 1896-1920; 1924-1926 (Box 2, Box 2A)
- Cornelia A. Upton
  - Two volumes of copies of letters and photographs to family from South America, 1896 (Box 3)
  - Journal, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Genealogy, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - U.S. flag used for U.S. minister to Bolivia, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from South America, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Biographical material, 1871-1934 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Centennial Exposition, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - White Mountains and Saguernay, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Travel, 1883; 1904 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Diaries, notes, and writings
    - Europe, 1886-1887 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Mt.Rainier; Camp in Paradise Park, 1904-1905 (Box 4, Folder 7, 10-11)
    - Colorado Circle, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Grand Canyon and San Diego, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Diploma, Providence High School, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, 1878-1934 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Silhouettes, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Line-a-day diaries, 1904-1918 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous travel notes, 1904-1905 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Letters from missionaries
    - Alaska, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - China, 1899-1927 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Japan, 1907-1911 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Near East, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Southern Mountains, South Dakota, Mexico, and India, 1913-1924 (Box 6, Folder 6)